<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://germslab.org/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org" />
<updated>2016-04-07T23:22:21+01:00</updated>
<id>http://germslab.org/</id>
<author>
  <name>Adina Howe</name>
  <uri>http://germslab.org/</uri>
  <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
</author>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[GERMS Is One!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org/blog/germs-is-one/" />
  <id>http://germslab.org/blog/germs-is-one</id>
  <published>2016-03-14T18:02:55+00:00</published>
  <updated>2016-03-14T18:02:55+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adina Howe</name>
    <uri>http://germslab.org</uri>
    <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;happy-birthday-germs&quot;&gt;Happy Birthday GERMS!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a difference a year makes!  We started out as a solo adventure, to two postdocs, to two graduate students (1 MS/1 PhD), to another postdoc, and its continued.  Currently, GERMS is comprised of a solid active team of 3 postdocs and 3 graduate students (3 PhD) (and one ‘me’).  We’re all VERY different but its been surprising how valuable these differences have been integral into shaping the dynamics of both this team and our values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to spend some time reflecting on the past year.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;best-accomplishment&quot;&gt;Best Accomplishment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been comparing the faculty gig to what I imagine (with no experience) running a start-up would feel like.  The most important goal of my year was to find the people that would make this job easy, fun, and rewarding. I am very committed to our team, and I have high expectations in each of our members to elevate everyone in our group.  Of the accomplishments of the year, I am most proud of our team and how we are working together, even in challenging circumstances – it’s not all been cake.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given my total disinterest in micromanagement, I’m glad that everyone is starting to find their groove in the science, administration, and projects.  I think everyone has switched projects at least a couple times this year (especially if they were with me from the beginning).  Certain projects that I thought were the most promising have not gained any traction while others have really taken off.  One postdoc learned so much that he was recruited out – a bittersweet success and its rewarding to know that the skills we’re training are useful to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The postdocs have undergone major transitions this year – they rapidly outgrow much of the mentorship I can provide and have started to really ‘own’ their projects.  They’ve pretty much set up (and are continuing to run) the entire lab for me, soooo grateful. Most of my interaction with the graduate students have been with training and the experience of graduate school more broadly (e.g., what classes to take, what skills to learn, what research one can do).  I can tell that the students are on the cusp of really accelerating and the summer is going to be a productive time.  They are already exceeding my expectations regularly.  Honestly, the hardest part of the job is keeping up and not being a clog in the stream.   By far, the most rewarding part of the year has been the team and the excitement of the things to come (weekly).  We’ve finally hit our groove in individual and group meetings – alternating between hackathon computational training with research talks weekly.  This took me longer than I thought it would to find the right rhythm of meetings. The other great thing about this group is that they are “givers”.  If there is an adjective that would describe all of them, it’d be either “giving” or “driven” – to find both of these in individuals in my opinion is a strange thing.  I don’t know how it happened honestly but it worked!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;most-valuable&quot;&gt;Most valuable&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides GERMS, one of the things I didn’t value enough coming in to this job was the power of awesome collaborators, both pre-award and post-award.  Our team benefits from very close relationships with our collaborators, so much so that many of my team are or will be co-advised by one of my collaborators.  One of the opportunities missed in my PhD was the benefits of a “committee” that was truly “committed” in my projects.  Our current collaboration is like a perfect committee for me.  My collaborators make sure that I am on track, actively make my job easier, bring deep and unique expertise, and are really invested in the commitment of the science we can do together.  On top of all these I-swear-I’m-not-exaggerating-awesomeness, they are really fun people to work with!  Honestly, I’ve never worked in a group of more invested senior scientists.  Finding them this year has taken nearly all stress of the “research” expectations of young faculty off my shoulders.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I’m having fun and not stressed, things usually work themselves out just fine.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth of the group has been a bit stressful on me, but its been a really positive change.  Though, I hope when I’m writing this review at the end of year 2, we haven’t grown much more (one more graduate student, that’s it!).  I’m very content with the size and productivity of our current group and have a real fear that changing things much more will ruin a great thing.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;going-forward&quot;&gt;Going forward&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its been a fantastic year.  And I have no doubt that this will continue next year.  Going forward, I’d like to make sure that I stay accessible to my teams and projects.  My goals next year will try to have creative energy within projects that I already have rather than creating new projects.  I want to make sure its a big year of growth for the graduate students, and a good year of finishing things while still creating enthusiasm for new projects for the postdocs.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Happy Birthday GERMS!  Glad you made it to year 1 - its like you’re real now!  :)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/blog/germs-is-one/&quot;&gt;GERMS Is One!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adina Howe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org&quot;&gt;Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems&lt;/a&gt; on March 14, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ryan Williams accepts position at Monsanto]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org/blog/ryan/" />
  <id>http://germslab.org/blog/ryan</id>
  <published>2016-01-21T21:03:25+00:00</published>
  <updated>2016-01-21T21:03:25+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adina Howe</name>
    <uri>http://germslab.org</uri>
    <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are sad to say goodbye to our dear pal Ryan as he continues his adventure at Monsanto in San Diego, CA and will help feed the world with his savvy data science skills.  Best of luck Ryan!  You’ll be missed!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/blog/ryan/&quot;&gt;Ryan Williams accepts position at Monsanto&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adina Howe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org&quot;&gt;Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems&lt;/a&gt; on January 21, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[National Pork Board funds GERMS research on manure management and antibiotic resistance]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org/blog/npb/" />
  <id>http://germslab.org/blog/npb</id>
  <published>2016-01-21T20:58:19+00:00</published>
  <updated>2016-01-21T20:58:19+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adina Howe</name>
    <uri>http://germslab.org</uri>
    <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Michelle Soupir collaborates with GERMS to lead an effort to understand the effects of manure application timing and management on the persistence and transport of antibiotics and antibiotic-resistant bacteria in corn and soybean production systems &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/research/&quot;&gt;Read more&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/blog/npb/&quot;&gt;National Pork Board funds GERMS research on manure management and antibiotic resistance&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adina Howe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org&quot;&gt;Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems&lt;/a&gt; on January 21, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[USDA awards GERMS Lab+ opportunity to develop DARTE-QM]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org/blog/darte/" />
  <id>http://germslab.org/blog/darte</id>
  <published>2016-01-21T20:54:47+00:00</published>
  <updated>2016-01-21T20:54:47+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adina Howe</name>
    <uri>http://germslab.org</uri>
    <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A fantastic collaboration with Iowa State University (Michelle Soupir), the USDA (Heather Allen and Tom Moorman), and Grinnell College (Shannon Hinsa) has resulted in a three year award to develop a high throughput quantitative monitoring for antibiotic resistance genes and transfer elements!  See more details on our &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/research/&quot;&gt;research page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/blog/darte/&quot;&gt;USDA awards GERMS Lab+ opportunity to develop DARTE-QM&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adina Howe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org&quot;&gt;Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems&lt;/a&gt; on January 21, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Phil Colgan Receives ISU Award]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org/blog/phil-colgan-receives-isu-award/" />
  <id>http://germslab.org/blog/phil-colgan-receives-isu-award</id>
  <published>2015-09-03T22:59:09+01:00</published>
  <updated>2015-09-03T22:59:09+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adina Howe</name>
    <uri>http://germslab.org</uri>
    <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;GERMS Phil Colgan received an Iowa State Presidential Scholarship, making him one of 20 top doctoral students in at Iowa State.  Phil is already doing great work innovating new approaches for pathogen detection in contaminated lake waters and understanding dynamic and often lethal responses in engineered systems.  Congratulations Phil!&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/blog/phil-colgan-receives-isu-award/&quot;&gt;Phil Colgan Receives ISU Award&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adina Howe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org&quot;&gt;Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems&lt;/a&gt; on September 03, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fan and Adina Teach Data Carpentry]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org/blog/fan-and-adina-teach-data-carpentry/" />
  <id>http://germslab.org/blog/fan-and-adina-teach-data-carpentry</id>
  <published>2015-08-30T23:02:11+01:00</published>
  <updated>2015-08-30T23:02:11+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adina Howe</name>
    <uri>http://germslab.org</uri>
    <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We successfully hosted our first Data Carpentry at Iowa State!  It was a huge success based on the feedback that the students want even MORE!  Jin was also an instructor for this course – the whole lab is helping to pay our training forward!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We covered the flow of data analysis in a typical genomics project and how one might automate many of the tasks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visit the course materials &lt;a href=&quot;http://datacarpentry.github.io/2015-08-24-ISU/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/blog/fan-and-adina-teach-data-carpentry/&quot;&gt;Fan and Adina Teach Data Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adina Howe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org&quot;&gt;Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems&lt;/a&gt; on August 30, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ryan and Adina Teach at NGS 2015]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org/blog/ryan-and-adina-teach-at-ngs-2015/" />
  <id>http://germslab.org/blog/ryan-and-adina-teach-at-ngs-2015</id>
  <published>2015-08-30T22:56:02+01:00</published>
  <updated>2015-08-30T22:56:02+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adina Howe</name>
    <uri>http://germslab.org</uri>
    <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;NGS 2015 was a great success and many of the students are working on awesome, impactful projects saving the world.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We covered lessons dealing with assembly and variant calling.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ryan tried out his new co-occurence tutorial.  See course materials at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://angus.readthedocs.org/en/2015/&quot;&gt;course website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/germs-lab/germs-lab.github.com/master/images/ngs-2015.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;alt&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/blog/ryan-and-adina-teach-at-ngs-2015/&quot;&gt;Ryan and Adina Teach at NGS 2015&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adina Howe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org&quot;&gt;Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems&lt;/a&gt; on August 30, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Website Updated]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org/blog/website-updated/" />
  <id>http://germslab.org/blog/website-updated</id>
  <published>2015-06-23T19:56:46+01:00</published>
  <updated>2015-06-23T19:56:46+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adina Howe</name>
    <uri>http://germslab.org</uri>
    <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I finally got around to updating the exciting new projects that our group is tackling.  Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/research/&quot;&gt;updated research page&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/blog/website-updated/&quot;&gt;Website Updated&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adina Howe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org&quot;&gt;Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems&lt;/a&gt; on June 23, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[GERMS Infection: Tomas Vetrovsky (Czech Academy of Sciences)]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org/blog/germs-infection-tomas-vetrovsky-czech-academy-of-sciences/" />
  <id>http://germslab.org/blog/germs-infection-tomas-vetrovsky-czech-academy-of-sciences</id>
  <published>2015-04-11T17:18:08+01:00</published>
  <updated>2015-04-11T17:18:08+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adina Howe</name>
    <uri>http://germslab.org</uri>
    <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tomas Vetrovsky from Petr Baldrian’s group of the Laboratory of Environmental Microbiology and the Institute of Microbiology CAS, Prague visited GERMS for two weeks this April.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked him to write a blog post about his experience here at ISU.  I’d also like to highlight Tomas’s fantastic game, Garden of Ants (see below),  that he developed which is a hybrid between a soil ecosystem and Starcraft.  It is in its alpha stage but very playable on both Mac and PC - we had a ton of fun with it.  You basically play the role of an ant colony trying to establish colonization in a fungal forest.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s his post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;most-memorable-things-about-visit&quot;&gt;Most memorable things about visit:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kind and open minded people&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wide possibilities for (self)realization&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chinese food &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-puzzles-me-about-americans&quot;&gt;What puzzles me about Americans:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Taxes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tips&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is a huge country&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;research-interests&quot;&gt;Research Interests:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ecology of microorganisms participating in organic matter transformation. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use of molecular biology methods including the high-throughput-sequencing (HTS) methods to analyze the genomes and transcriptomes of isolated strains and environmental metagenomes and metatranscriptomes. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bioinformatics, data analysis and development of software tools.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social insects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tools-that-i-share&quot;&gt;Tools that I share:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SEED&lt;/strong&gt; - is a free-to-use GUI-based sequence editor and pipeline for fast bioinformatic analysis of PCR amplicons on desktop computers according to the suggested workflow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.biomed.cas.cz/mbu/lbwrf/seed/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SEED main page&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.biomed.cas.cz/mbu/lbwrf/seed/wiki/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SEED wiki (under construction)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;garden-of-ants&quot;&gt;Garden of Ants&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Garden of Ants&lt;/strong&gt; - is a platform independent real-time strategy written in java. The game simulates a living strategy of hypothetical ant species &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atta_%28genus%29&quot;&gt;it is mainly inspired by leaf cutting ants - Atta&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/vetrot/garden-of-ants/wiki/Home&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Garden of Ants wiki&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/vetrot/garden-of-ants/downloads&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Garden of Ants demo (password: “jamoebix”)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/blog/germs-infection-tomas-vetrovsky-czech-academy-of-sciences/&quot;&gt;GERMS Infection: Tomas Vetrovsky (Czech Academy of Sciences)&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adina Howe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org&quot;&gt;Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems&lt;/a&gt; on April 11, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[In the ISU News]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org/articles/in-the-isu-news/" />
  <id>http://germslab.org/articles/in-the-isu-news</id>
  <published>2015-02-19T14:24:43+00:00</published>
  <updated>2015-02-19T14:24:43+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adina Howe</name>
    <uri>http://germslab.org</uri>
    <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The GERMS lab is featured in the Iowa State University College of Engineering &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.engineering.iastate.edu/2015/02/19/the-impacts-of-the-invisible-how-microbes-affect-our-lives/&quot;&gt;news&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/articles/in-the-isu-news/&quot;&gt;In the ISU News&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adina Howe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org&quot;&gt;Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems&lt;/a&gt; on February 19, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Got Algae?]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org/blog/got-algae/" />
  <id>http://germslab.org/blog/got-algae</id>
  <published>2015-02-14T03:31:47+00:00</published>
  <updated>2015-02-14T03:31:47+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adina Howe</name>
    <uri>http://germslab.org</uri>
    <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;germs-infect-bioprocess-algae&quot;&gt;GERMS infect Bioprocess Algae&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GERMS lab traveled to Shenandoah, Iowa (taking the scenic route
through Missouri and Nebraska because we were to geeked out in our
science conversations).  There, we were hosted by Joshua Livermore
(Mr. Algae Pro) of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bioprocessalgae.com&quot;&gt;Bioprocess Algae&lt;/a&gt;.
Sustainably located right next to an ethanol plant, it was a terrific
exploration of how one can grow algae in the middle of wintry Iowa and
how managing microbial resources can make real economic impact as this
industry begins to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We sadly forgot to take a photo of ourselves in front of the plant
with Mr. Algae Pro, but we did make it to the not-to-be-missed
windmill in Elk Horn, Iowa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fantastic trip, with hopefully a future visit and collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/germs-lab/germs-lab.github.com/master/images/algae_day_happy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;alt&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/blog/got-algae/&quot;&gt;Got Algae?&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adina Howe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org&quot;&gt;Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems&lt;/a&gt; on February 14, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[GERMS Research Presentation to ENVSCI690]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org/articles/germs-research-presentation-to-envsci690/" />
  <id>http://germslab.org/articles/germs-research-presentation-to-envsci690</id>
  <published>2015-02-09T19:49:23+00:00</published>
  <updated>2015-02-09T19:49:23+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adina Howe</name>
    <uri>http://germslab.org</uri>
    <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/adinachuanghowe/isu-envsci690-graduate-seminar-slides&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt; from presentation to ISU’s graduate seminar (ENSCI690)&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/articles/germs-research-presentation-to-envsci690/&quot;&gt;GERMS Research Presentation to ENVSCI690&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adina Howe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org&quot;&gt;Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems&lt;/a&gt; on February 09, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[PhD Student Wanted: Impact Carbon Cyling in Soil]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org/articles/phd-student-wanted-impact-carbon-cyling-in-soil/" />
  <id>http://germslab.org/articles/phd-student-wanted-impact-carbon-cyling-in-soil</id>
  <published>2015-02-08T04:52:47+00:00</published>
  <updated>2015-02-08T04:52:47+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adina Howe</name>
    <uri>http://germslab.org</uri>
    <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This position has been filled.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phd-integrating-climate-change-microbial-ecology-land-use-environmental-sciences-microbiology-and-data-sciences&quot;&gt;PhD integrating climate change, microbial ecology, land use, environmental sciences, microbiology, and data sciences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GERMS Laboratory at Iowa State University is looking for an enthusiastic, motivated PhD student to help develop novel methods to identify the microbial carbon drivers in bioenergy crop soils and to improve current climate models with microbial datasets.  The impact of this research can help sustainable land management policy and identify microbial benefits for soil health and productivity.  This position will provide you with the opportunity to learn and work with cutting edge molecular methods and datasets for environmental microbiology and microbial ecology.  This position will be mainly data-driven, though opportunities to participate, implement, and design experiments exist.  You will have the opportunity to collaborate closely with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://kirstenhofmockel.org/&quot;&gt;Hofmockel Laboratory&lt;/a&gt; at ISU.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Qualifications:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Strong organizational and record keeping skills.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Effective oral and written communication skills.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ability to interact with an interdisciplinary team. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Previous research experience.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interest in data analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Preferred&lt;/em&gt; – background in microbiology and/or bioinformatics, experience with a programming language. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in this position, you should apply to the ISU graduate program in Agricultural and Biosystems Engineering, Environmental Science, Interdepartmental Microbiology Program, or Bioinformatics and Computational Biology.  This position is available immediately.  Contact germs.research@gmail.com with any questions.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/articles/phd-student-wanted-impact-carbon-cyling-in-soil/&quot;&gt;PhD Student Wanted: Impact Carbon Cyling in Soil&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adina Howe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org&quot;&gt;Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems&lt;/a&gt; on February 08, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[PhD Student Wanted:  Impact Water Quality]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org/articles/phd-student-microbial-measurements-of-water-quality/" />
  <id>http://germslab.org/articles/phd-student-microbial-measurements-of-water-quality</id>
  <published>2015-02-08T04:47:06+00:00</published>
  <updated>2015-02-08T04:47:06+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adina Howe</name>
    <uri>http://germslab.org</uri>
    <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This position has been filled * &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phd-integrating-global-change-microbial-ecology-environmental-sciences-limnology-and-data-sciences&quot;&gt;PhD integrating global change, microbial ecology, environmental sciences, limnology, and data sciences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GERMS Laboratory at Iowa State University is looking for an enthusiastic, motivated PhD student to help develop novel methods to assess the biological, chemical, and physical integrity of waters by integrating genomic microbial characterization with an extensive water quality monitoring program.  The impact of this research can transform traditional water quality indicators and provide critical insight into how water quality is monitored and evaluated. This position will provide you with the opportunity to learn and work with cutting edge molecular methods for environmental microbiology and analysis of a variety of datasets.  We provide an inter-disciplinary training opportunity, and you will train with scientists with expertise in microbiology, limnology, environmental science, and bioinformatics.   You will also have the opportunity to collaborate closely with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.public.iastate.edu/~downing/&quot;&gt;ISU Limnology Laboratory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Qualifications:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Strong organizational and record keeping skills.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Effective oral and written communication skills.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ability to interact with an interdisciplinary team. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Previous research experience.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interest in data analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Preferred&lt;/em&gt; – background in microbiology and/or bioinformatics, experience with a programming language. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in this position, you should apply to the ISU graduate program in Agricultural and Biosystems Engineering, Environmental Science, Interdepartmental Microbiology Program, or Bioinformatics and Computational Biology.  The ideal start date is May, 2015.   Contact germs.research@gmail.com with any questions.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/articles/phd-student-microbial-measurements-of-water-quality/&quot;&gt;PhD Student Wanted:  Impact Water Quality&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adina Howe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org&quot;&gt;Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems&lt;/a&gt; on February 08, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Python in Nature News]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org/articles/python-in-nature-news/" />
  <id>http://germslab.org/articles/python-in-nature-news</id>
  <published>2015-02-05T17:25:34+00:00</published>
  <updated>2015-02-05T17:25:34+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adina Howe</name>
    <uri>http://germslab.org</uri>
    <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Python and our group featured in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/news/programming-pick-up-python-1.16833&quot;&gt;Nature News article&lt;/a&gt;!  Does this count as a Nature pub?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/articles/python-in-nature-news/&quot;&gt;Python in Nature News&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adina Howe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org&quot;&gt;Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems&lt;/a&gt; on February 05, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[GERMS Defined]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org/blog/germs-defined/" />
  <id>http://germslab.org/blog/germs-defined</id>
  <published>2015-01-26T00:19:43+00:00</published>
  <updated>2015-01-26T00:19:43+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adina Howe</name>
    <uri>http://germslab.org</uri>
    <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I spent some time thinking about my vision and mission for our group
for a
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/adinachuanghowe/adinas-faculty-introduction-isu-abe&quot;&gt;faculty presentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure this will evolve with my group but here it is…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;mission&quot;&gt;Mission&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are changing the environment that we live in. To preserve our
environmental integrity, we must understand and manage the impacts of
global change. Scientific research must inform our decisions and policy.
Therefore, we use innovative scientific methods to evaluate and understand our complex and changing natural world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;vision&quot;&gt;Vision&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To provide scalable, quantitative tools to monitor microbial responses in complex environments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To identify the microbial drivers responding to global change in complex environments (e.g., soils, waters, gut)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To predict and model the impacts of microbial responses on ecosystem health and services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the adventure begins…&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/blog/germs-defined/&quot;&gt;GERMS Defined&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adina Howe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org&quot;&gt;Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems&lt;/a&gt; on January 26, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Faster Metagenomic Assembly?]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org/articles/faster-metagenomic-assembly/" />
  <id>http://germslab.org/articles/faster-metagenomic-assembly</id>
  <published>2014-10-09T21:23:49+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-10-09T21:23:49+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adina Howe</name>
    <uri>http://germslab.org</uri>
    <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Super fast improvement for metagenomic assembly, hope to test this soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It finished assembling a soil metagenomics dataset with 252Gbps in 44.1 hours and 99.6 hours on a single computing node with and without a GPU, respectively.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/abs/1409.7208&quot;&gt;Preprint&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pathogenomenick/status/515390848230760448&quot;&gt;The hype&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ivory.idyll.org/blog/2014-how-good-is-megahit.html&quot;&gt;A very helpful blog from Titus Brown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/articles/faster-metagenomic-assembly/&quot;&gt;Faster Metagenomic Assembly?&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adina Howe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org&quot;&gt;Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems&lt;/a&gt; on October 09, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Boarding Pass to Mars]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org/blog/boarding-pass-to-mars/" />
  <id>http://germslab.org/blog/boarding-pass-to-mars</id>
  <published>2014-10-09T15:29:33+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-10-09T15:29:33+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adina Howe</name>
    <uri>http://germslab.org</uri>
    <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here….we….go…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://mars.nasa.gov/participate/send-your-name/orion-first-flight/?action=getcert&amp;amp;e=1&amp;amp;cn=322916&quot; width=&quot;750&quot; height=&quot;307&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get a boarding pass too, &lt;a href=&quot;http://mars.nasa.gov/participate/send-your-name/orion-first-flight/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/blog/boarding-pass-to-mars/&quot;&gt;Boarding Pass to Mars&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adina Howe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org&quot;&gt;Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems&lt;/a&gt; on October 09, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Plans for the Lab]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org/blog/plans-for-the-lab/" />
  <id>http://germslab.org/blog/plans-for-the-lab</id>
  <published>2014-09-29T15:36:53+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-09-29T15:36:53+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adina Howe</name>
    <uri>http://germslab.org</uri>
    <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a repost from Adina’s &lt;a href=&quot;adina.github.io&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;. Since it was lab-relevant, I included it here.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-next-adventure&quot;&gt;The Next Adventure&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting in January, 2015, I will be beginning my adventure at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iastate.edu/&quot;&gt;Iowa State University&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.abe.iastate.edu&quot;&gt;Agricultural and Biosystems Engineering&lt;/a&gt;.  There, I’ll be leading up the &lt;a href=&quot;germslab.org&quot;&gt;GERMS lab&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot understate how excited I am about this and how grateful I am to have this opportunity and for the help along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-plans&quot;&gt;My Plans&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read my application material on the lab website, but I summarize the gist of it here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My personal goals for this lab are simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use what I’ve learned to make measurable impacts on understanding and managing the microbes around us&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create an energetic and productive environment for research&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mentor students to become outstanding researchers and people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m looking forward to continue some of my on-going research:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understanding the awesome diversity of microbes around us and how to model and manage their impacts on our lives&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exploring the impacts of viruses on these communities and our health and environment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Development of methods for environmental omic-based methods, connecting the dots between sequencing technologies and understanding complex microbial communities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some directions I’m looking forward to exploring include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moving beyond metagenomic discovery and characterization towards modeling and managing communities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving the available biomarkers to detect and quantify pathogens and antibiotic genes in the environment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing open-source eductational resources and classes making computational biology more assessible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exploring big data and the role of microbial data in predictive agriculture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many many more…I’m very much looking forward to all the collaborative opportunities at Iowa State.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/blog/plans-for-the-lab/&quot;&gt;Plans for the Lab&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adina Howe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org&quot;&gt;Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems&lt;/a&gt; on September 29, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[GERMS First Blogpost]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://germslab.org/blog/germs-first-blogpost/" />
  <id>http://germslab.org/blog/germs-first-blogpost</id>
  <published>2014-09-02T22:58:01+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-09-02T22:58:01+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adina Howe</name>
    <uri>http://germslab.org</uri>
    <email>germs.research@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to our blogpost.  We hope this is the beginning of many to come.  Right now, we are trying to fill our ranks with enthusiastic and curious folks which can contribute to this blog!  Until then, please check back!&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org/blog/germs-first-blogpost/&quot;&gt;GERMS First Blogpost&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adina Howe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://germslab.org&quot;&gt;Genomics and Environmental Research in Microbial Systems&lt;/a&gt; on September 02, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>